<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvedding-ring, fitted to the finger of euery paire that haue or shall meete in the feare of God: or, That diuine circle of heauenly loue, wherein man and wife should walke all their dayes The posie whereof is an expression of a good husbands kindnesse toward his vertuous wife, with her retaliacion of like affection.</title>
            <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121236</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856421</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856421</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1444:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvedding-ring, fitted to the finger of euery paire that haue or shall meete in the feare of God: or, That diuine circle of heauenly loue, wherein man and wife should walke all their dayes The posie whereof is an expression of a good husbands kindnesse toward his vertuous wife, with her retaliacion of like affection.</title>
                  <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 36, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Eliz. Allde for Edward Blount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: W. Crompton.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21970:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21970:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VVEDDING-RING, FITTED TO THE FINGER OF EVERY PAIRE THAT HAVE OR SHALL MEETE IN THE FEARE OF GOD: OR, THAT DIVINE CIRCLE OF HEAVENLY LOVE, WHEREIN man and wife ſhould walke all their dayes. THE POSIE WHEREOF IS AN expreſſion of A good Husbands Kindneſſe towards his vertuous wife, with her retaliacion of like affection.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Woodcut printer's device showing an old man standing beside an olive tree; above him, on a scroll, the motto 'Noli altum sapere' (McKerrow, 310).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by ELIZ. ALLDE for EDWARD BLOVNT. 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21970:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21970:2"/>
            <head>To my worthy and much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red friends, M aſter <hi>William Hackwill</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, one of his Maieſties Iuſtices of Peace for the Countie of Buckingham, with his truely ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and religious Bedfellow, Miſtris <hi>Elizabeth Hackwill,</hi> the dew of Heauen, and fatneſſe of the Earth, Grace and Peace bee multiplied in Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orſhipfull, and right dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued: I haue often ſought oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to ſalute you ioyntly; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging my ſelfe your deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor many wayes, &amp; which is more; vnable to ſatisfie any: it was the griefe of <hi>Darius,</hi> that he ſhould die indebted to his friend, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting he bewayled, as his laſt, not his leaſt miſ-hap, hauing receiued a courteſie, hee ſhould not liue to requite it. if ſuch an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement
<pb facs="tcp:21970:3"/> may not goe in part of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I might deſpaire; hauing receiued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from you, both while J liued neere you, as ſince my remouall at your motion, into theſe parts (diſtance of place hath not ſtopt the current of affection, nor abſence begot obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion) and yet find my ſelfe able to doe no more: onely this is my comfort, Good-will hath not beene wanting; if abilitie anſwered deſire, you ſhould find me as readie to pay, as to confeſſe: J would not faigne a debt; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it, the propertie of inſinuating flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; neither would I denie it, where it is due, the guiſe of ſeruile baſeneſſe; iudging it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thus to publiſh my owne pouertie, then to be cenſured as vngratefull, or of my friends forgetfull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preaching at the Marriage of Mr. <hi>Iohn Berrie.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Occaſion</hi> lately directed my meditations vpon this ſubiect: wherein the mutuall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of your choyce, did often preſent it ſelfe vnto my thoughts; the matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of handling;</p>
            <p>(If the teſtimonie of an experienſt friend
<pb facs="tcp:21970:3"/> may be thought impartiall) applying it ſelfe moſt fully &amp; fitly to you both; that I could not forbeare to impart it as a meſſenger of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, no worke of worth; except you bee pleaſed by acceptation, to make it worth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing: here you may read your ſelues, and be ſtir'd vp to bleſſe God, the maker of Marriages, for his good prouidence in your meeting; here you may ſee that Wedding-ring, which you both put on, in conceit and reſolution, at the Marriage-day; that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Circle or heauenly round of heartie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting-loue, wherein you doe, and all mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſons ſhould moue during life; to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their owne vertuous mates, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling others; am I deceiued? or experience hath taught mee what I haue written: no more: neither may I ſpeake; what I haue ſeene and obſerued, of your happineſſe in this kind: liue long more happy; it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to pray, as <hi>Ioab</hi> for <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.3.</note> The Lord your God adde vnto it an hundred-fold, that your eyes may ſee it: the Lord increaſe
<pb facs="tcp:21970:4"/> your content daily, and double the portion of the ſauing graces of his Spirit vpon you both: otherwiſe I cannot ſteed you; prayers you ſhall not want, while I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my ſtudie in</hi> Barſtaple, <date>Ianuary 1. 1630.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. CROMPTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21970:4"/>
            <head>A VVEDDING-RING: FITTED TO THE FINGER of euery Paire, that haue or ſhall meete in the feare of God.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROVERBS 31.29.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Many-daughters haue done vertuouſly, but thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleſt them all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the tenth verſe of this Chapter to the end thereof, (<hi>Reuerend,</hi> right Worſhipfull and all dearely beloued,) you haue, and at leaſure may read, an <hi>Artificiall</hi> Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-ſong; or a diuine Hymn, deſcribing and commending Marriage with vertuous women: pen'd or appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as may be probably conceiued, to be ſaid or ſung at <hi>Solemne</hi> meetings; eſpecially vpon ſuch occaſions; euery verſe begins with a letter of the <hi>Hebrew Alphabet,</hi> in order from the beginning to the end: compoſed much after the maner of thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21970:5"/> 
               <hi>Pſhalmes</hi> of degrees with <hi>Rhethoricall</hi> gradations:<note place="margin">Pſal 110.121.122.123.124.125, &amp;c.</note> partly they might be more ſweetly vttered; either in parts by many, or altogether by one, to the greater content of the ſpeaker, profit of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and delight of both; partly the matter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, might be with more caſe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and longer retained.</p>
            <p>In it ſelfe, it is a Propheſie, containing much good counſell, therefore called, (if I miſtake not) <hi>The Crowne of</hi> Solomon:<note place="margin">Cant 3.11.</note> good <hi>Counſell</hi> to a King, reſpectiuely, about the choyce of a wife, is as his <hi>Crowne,</hi> or the Crowne of his Crowne, for the conſolation of all true hearted ſubiects and preſeruation of the publike-weale.</p>
            <p>Goe forth, O ye Daughters of <hi>Zion,</hi> and behold <hi>King Solomon,</hi> with the <hi>Crowne,</hi> wherewith his mother crowned him, in the day of his eſpouſals, and in the day of the gladneſſe of his heart: that Crowne I take to be this Propheſie; wherein, as out of a ſparkling Diamond, you may ſee the refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting image of true beauty, and read both the worke and worth of a good woman: and fitly may it he called a Crowne: euery wife thus quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, is a Crowne to her husband, ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi> elſewhere;<note place="margin">Prou. 12 4.</note> her vertues &amp; graces are as ſo many Rubies or glittering Pearles of great price, which doe well become and adorne a Crowne: Goe forth therefore, O ye Daughters of <hi>Zion,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Solomon</hi> with his Crowne, whereon we find this Poſie ingrauen as with a pen of iron, in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21970:5"/> of gold, neuer to be forgotten.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The price of a vertuous woman is farre aboue Rubies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take notice firſt of her fidelity:<note place="margin">Verſes 11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the heart of her husband doth ſafely truſt in her; free from thoſe boiſterous ſtormes of iealouſie, and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting cares about houſe-hold affaires, whereby others are toſt day and night, he reſts himſelfe in quiet repoſe, like a ſhippe at <hi>Anchor</hi> in the calme harbour, knowing his wife will anſwere her truſt, being neuer idle, nor ill imployed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of her induſtry, ſhee ſeeketh wooll,<note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> and flaxe, and worketh willingly; delayes not, till materialls inuite her, but ſends &amp; ſeekes; her thoughts preuent occaſion; her hands and eyes contend with time, ſhe doth thoſe things freely, which others may doe, conſtrained through feare or neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of her vigilancy,<note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> ſhe riſes while it is yet night; diligence expels drowſineſſe, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches good wiues to remoue darkneſſe by an artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Sunne, that the goodneſſe of God in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching-light, may be opportunely met (not meritoriouſly matcht) with ſome good worke of theirs: weakeneſſe I know tyes many, but ſloth more, too long in bed; <hi>lazie</hi> humours are beſt purged by early riſing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, of her charity: ſhe ſtretcheth forth her hands to the poore and needy;<note place="margin">Verſe 20.</note> like ſome pleaſant riuer ſhe feeds and clothes the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21970:6"/> valleies, which through the heat of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or the cold of pouerty, were ready to pine away; hungry bellies and naked armes are the ſubiect of her meditation, it is not enough others know her to be good, except they feele it; help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full compaſſion is a marke of true deuotion while ſhe feeds or clothes her body with rich dainties, ſhe is obſerued to ſigh and ſay, What abundance doe I enioy, when many a good ſoule wants neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries? her fulneſſe yeelds no ſatisfaction, vnleſſe it ouerſlow by communication.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, of her prouidence in gouerning her lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Kingdome;<note place="margin">Verſe 21.22, 23, 24.</note> like a well-ordered Army, euery one furniſht, hath his place of employment aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned; Lawes enacted; houres of examination appointed; &amp; leſt ſhe ſhould erre in iudgement, ſhe lookes well to the wayes of her houſe-hold, her eyes are in euery corner: children learning, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants labouring, all obedient to the becke of her hand and eye, ſuch ſoueraignety ſhines in the face of vertue: ſhe giues maidens a portion; their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh ſingers may not be their owne carners, who care as little in the ſpending, as they did in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Maſters eſtate; ſhe clothes her family with ſcarlet, the laſting-weed of deſerued honour; implying what ſhee is, and deſerues to haue: makes her ſelfe carpets of tapeſtry; the furniture of her houſe and table is the fruit of her hands, made, not bought; ornaments in a Family are commendable Emblemes of pious induſtry, as more vſefull things; God allowing not onely to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21970:6"/> ſuſtaine, but to delight Nature: ſhe keepes her husband euer in that decent faſhion of attyre, which becomes his age and calling, ſo that he is ſpecially noted when he ſits in the gates, amongſt the chiefe of the Land: no paines about him is grieuous to her, for whoſe ſake all the reſt are chearefully vndertaken.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, of her wiſedome and diſcretion;<note place="margin">Verſe 26.</note> in ſpeech ſhe openeth her mouth with wiſdome, her words are few, ſeaſonable and weighty: attire, not curious nor careleſſe, but ſuch as the time allowes in modeſt &amp; graue Matrons: ſtrength and honour are her clothing: &amp; for behauiour; in her tongue is the law of kindneſſe, ſhe prouokes none to euill thoughts by lightnes; neither ſends any from her diſcontented, through ſowre, ſullen, and heauy ſadnes; her carriage is ſo ſweetly tempered with modeſty and humility, that at once ſhe cheares the vertuous and curbs the vicious-minded.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, her piety, ſhe feares the Lord,<note place="margin">Verſe 30.</note> which is a corner ſtone in this building, the foundation of all; what good ſhe doth, is in obedience vnto God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and will be conſtant in doing, till the Lord leaue commanding:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> The la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Iewell.</note> but of this I haue ſpoken enough already, vpon another occaſion, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the two laſt verſes of this Chapter. Who hath or can finde ſuch a vertuous woman? her ſelfe is portion enough, ſhe paſſes her waight in gold: her dwelling is a repreſentation of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; <hi>O happy man,</hi> and therefore happy, becauſe husband to ſuch a wife, who brings ioyfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21970:7"/> to his heart, delight to his eyes, glory to his head, and helpes him keepe a continuall feaſt. <hi>Adam</hi> might haue had a garden, no <hi>Paradiſe</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Eue;</hi> man is imperfect without a wife, vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py without a good one; what the heauens haue bin thought to be aboue him, and his ſoule with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, that a vertuous wife is indeed about him, like well-tuned Virginals, her life is perfect Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke: no harſh ſounds, nor iarring ſtrings on her breſt: if ſhe intreat, it is with humility; if ſhe complaine, it is with teares; if ſhe chide, it is with ſmiles: how can ſhe diſpleaſe, whoſe harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thoughts are ſtill intent to pleaſe? he hath put off nature, that finds no content in ſuch a Turtle; not to acknowledge ſuch a helper, argues want of grace: let him ſeeke her that wants one, let him mourne that hath loſt one, let him praiſe her that enioyes one; ſo much is implyed in the Text. <hi>Her husband</hi> alſo he praiſes her, ſaying,
<q>Many daughters haue done vertuouſly, but thou excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The words are a concluſiue branch of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie; a ſpeech of praiſe deliuered in the perſon of an experienſt husband, and grounded vpon obſeruation:</p>
            <p>Deuiding themſelues into
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Commendation, and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Compariſon.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21970:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Commendation</hi> of vertuous daughters, with their number: Many daughters haue done ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compariſon,</hi> wherein one ſo qualified is prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all, But thou excelleſt them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daughters</hi> carry their duty in their name:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> A radicae. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> A diſicare.</note> the word in the Originall ſprings from a root, which ſignifies, A building, or to build; and may yeeld vs a twofold inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that euery vertuous daughter is a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and therefore in the creation of woman, it is ſaid, that the Lord built her of the ribbe; as men vſe to doe ſtately houſes, faire, ſtrong,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.22.</note> and well-ſeated, for their delight and profit; without which they cannot well be. VVhat <hi>Tiſaphernes</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant to the Perſian King ſpake once of <hi>Alcybia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> comparing him to a faire houſe of pleaſure,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plul. in vit. Aleybiades.</hi> See the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets prayer Pſal. 144.12</note> is truely verified of a vertuous daughter; ſhe is a building both delightfull and fruitfull. Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for ſtatelineſſe and profit, to a Merchants ſhip, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.14. Now in all buildings, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue coſt, comelineſſe, and vſe; no leſſe in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous daughters; comely they are to the eye, many wayes beneficiall, and they want no coſt, will ſpare none, or elſe none ſhould be ſpared for their good: they are the Lords building,<note place="margin">Pſa. 122.3.</note> like Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, a houſe that is compact together at vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it ſelfe: not like the dropping houſe,<note place="margin">Pro. 19.13.27.15.</note> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Prouerbes, but like our Sauiours houſe built vpon a rocke;<note place="margin">Math. 7, 24</note> which proues a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21970:8"/> defence for the owner, againſt the boiſtrous winds of violent aſſaults, and the ſcorching <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine</hi> of alluring temptations, for outward ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of ſeuerall parts in order, for inward furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, gifts and graces of the mind, admirable: obſerue and ſee, the foundation, turrets, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, doores, inner-chambers, all hanged with rich iewels of intellectuall vertues, and diuine graces, and you will ſay, This onely deſerues the name of <hi>None ſuch:</hi> no building to the ſight ſo pleaſant, none for vſe ſo profitable, as this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,<note place="margin">Spirabile Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. Bodin. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> mouing, ſpeaking Tabernacle: I might ſtay you ouer-long in the Entry; ſhould I ſtand to vnuaile the whole Fabricke: you may admire the reſt by what you ſee a farre off, I dare but point to it, and paſſe away: excellency in any workemanſhip, calles for an exact or no deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; leſt fruitleſſe haſte ſhould eclipſe the praiſe and glory of the Workeman.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>Secondly, euery vertuous daughter is, and muſt be a builder; we haue ſeene what ſhe is, idle ſhe may not be, her name implies ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as tends to perfection: a builder ſhe is, firſt, to her decayed parents, by vpholding the credit of an ancient family, by renewing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing their name, and nature with poſterity, &amp; by repairing the breach, age hath made in the ruinous houſes of their bodies, with a timely ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of all their wants;<note place="margin">Pro. 23.22.</note> a vertuous daughter makes old parents begin to liue young againe, partly by feeling preſent comforts, and partly by fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21970:8"/> vpon hopes of future happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſhe is a builder together with her husband, as copartner, yoke-fellow,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> and helpe meete for him, in the worke committed to their truſt; if one ſhould build, and the other pull downe, we might expect a Babel, no proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous building; but <hi>Solomon</hi> tels vs,<note place="margin">Pro. 14.1.</note> euery wiſe woman builds her houſe, the fooliſh onely plucke it downe with their hands; and that was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon his building in the later end, went ſo backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly-forward,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 1.3, 4, 7, 8.</note> hauing ſo many vicious daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters about him: a good woman raiſes vp the ruines of decayed places, ſtudying how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue her husbands credit and good name, both in regard of God and men; when the contrary, makes the ſtatelieſt turrets ſtoup, through pride,<note place="margin">O domus anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua quam diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri domino domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naris?</note> ryot and idleneſſe, diſmantling ancient monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſtrength, to bury her husbands honour in the rubbiſh thereof: the dwelling of one is like the pleaſant ſpring, euen in the middeſt of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, freſh, gay, and pleaſant: the houſe of the other, like ſtormy VVinter, in the middle of May, torne, ragged, and ill-fauoured:<note place="margin">Pro. 24.30, 31.</note> I went by the field of the ſlothfull, and loe, it was all growne ouer with thornes, and nettles, and the ſtone wall thereof was broken downe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſhe is a builder in regard of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, inſtrumentally to giue them being,<note place="margin">Education of children is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale.</note> and well-being, both for conception, birth, and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, by her induſtrious care, tender infants at firſt, like vnto the creeping Iuy on the wall,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21970:9"/> come to be tall and goodly <hi>Cedars</hi> in <hi>Libanon,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable pieces to vnderprop a declining ſtate; whoſoeuer knowes, hath ſeene or heard of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, what it is to beare and bring vp children, will ſay, that ſhe is a painefull builder: her <hi>nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous</hi> pangs before, &amp; ſleepeleſſe nights after the birth, when variety of change cannot alter, nor giue content to her teareleſſe cryer; one while ſhe ſits and ſings, to deceiue or flatter the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of time, with counterfeited mirth; anon ſhe ſighs and weepes, (the burden of her ſong,) and ſings againe,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16.</note> as if variety did eaſe, though not remoue her griefe; all which doe ſufficiently tell vs, her building in this kind, is multiplyed ſorrow.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſhe is a builder to her ſelfe, of a good name,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.1.</note> which is a rare monument, better then precious oynment, rather to be ſought then great riches,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.1.</note> no ſhining titles of fading glory ſo famous, no glittering trophies of ancient Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies ſo durable, as this building: a vertuous daughter cannot be obſcured, no more then a City built on a hill, Fame borrowing the tongues of ſtrangers to publiſh her deſert: euery action ſpeakes of her, and euen while ſhe ſleepes, the building goes forward.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, ſhe is a builder in regard of her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, either by confection of ſalues, diſtillation of waters, or preparation of other neceſſaries for their reliefe, ſupply, and ſuccour in time of need: a vortuous daughter is a true neighbour,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21970:9"/> euery one neere her is the better for her; Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency beares ſuch ſway in her, and is ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preualent, that ſhe cannot thinke of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury with delight, either to doe it to another, or to reuenge it, done to her ſelfe by others; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will her habituall goodneſſe ſuffer her to be a careleſſe helper; when Satan hath ſowne the ſeeds of ſtrife and diſcord, and ſtird vp men by diuiſion, to weaken themſelues with their owne, hands, ſhe ſleeps not, till thoſe tares be pluckt vp, and peace and loue replanted in their affections.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, ſhe is a builder, in regard of the Church and Common-weale, though ſhe may not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikely be ſeene, in her retiring roomes, ſhe helps forward the building by prayers, teares, aduice, and the labour of her hands: like the wiſe hearted-women vnder the Law, who are commended by the Lord himſelfe, as builders,<note place="margin">Exod. 35.25.</note> euery one prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; bringing ſomething towards the finiſhing of the Tabernacle: let not women be diſcouraged, becauſe they are not called to publike offices, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous daughters want not imployment,<note place="margin">Familia pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter inſtituta ciuitatis imago, Bodin, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> neither are they excluded, (as ſome vnwiſely-ambitious, haue repiningly-murmured,) from this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſeruice; by their priuate diligence in pious, exerciſes, the Magiſtrate rules, the Miniſter tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the husband-man labours,<note place="margin">Right orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, is a branch of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal diſcipline.</note> the Phyſician cures, the Lawyer pleades, and the Souldier fights the better: let them not thinke themſelues therefore contemned, or that they can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe they doe not euery thing, God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21970:10"/> hath wiſely diſpoſed of his creatures into ſeuerall rankes, as an expert Captaine doth his Army, allotting euery one ſuch and ſo many talents, as his place required; be content with your portion, the lot is fallen out vnto you in a good ground.</p>
            <p>And ſo you ſee the ſubiect of this commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>A daughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She</hi> is a delectable building, onely let her be mindefull, that ſhe weary not her Lord, with ouer much needleſſe reparation; ſhe muſt auoid fantaſtike faſhions, curious gawdineſſe, with all vaine ſuperficiall trimmings; ſuch printed paper-houſes pleaſes children onely, but cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a ſtorme, and are iuſtly derided by euery vnderſtanding paſſenger.</p>
            <p>She is a conſcionable builder, let her remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſhe be not idle, nor ſluggliſh in her labour, but like the ſpinning-Spider, or the gathering-Bee, let her daily bring ſome hony to the hiue: &amp; in this common lation of a daughter, we haue three things commended to our obſeruation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the neceſſity and benefit of Hiſtory, to record the vertuous deeds of ſuch daughters: the phraſe here vſed implies ſo much; preſuppoſing a Catalogue of names, laid before the Pen man of this Propheſie, <hi>(Many daughters:)</hi> Hiſtory vnto memory, is as a good wife vnto her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, a helpe meet for him; in regard of truth, both the mother, and nurce thereof, if the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer be a man experienſt in the affaires he treates of, iudicious and impartiall: it is a faithfull
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21970:10"/> truſty Councellour of ſtate, by whoſe aduice and direction a Common-weale may be framed, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, reformed and preſerued; an Army orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, enemies vanquiſht, victory obtained: wee read of <hi>Lucius Lucullus</hi> appointed Captaine Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ouer the <hi>Romane</hi> Forces againſt <hi>Mithridates,</hi> hauing no experience or knowledge in warre,<note place="margin">Praeſat. vit. Plutarch.</note> more then he had gotten by reading Hiſtory, and yet proued a diſcreet &amp; valiant Commander, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing at that time, two of the greateſt <hi>Eaſterne</hi> Princes. It is and may be the directour of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men in any of their actions; wherein they may ſee without danger, how others haue beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues vpon ſeuerall occaſions, and what hath followed: ſpeculatiue experience yeelds the cheapeſt wiſedome.</p>
            <p>It is a puniſher of vice, preſenting aged folly, greene and freſh to poſterity, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſinne to dye, much leſſe to bee bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in obliuion: the name of the wicked ſhall rot, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Prou. 10.7.</note> the euill ſauour of their filthy life, ſhall be conueyed through Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory to generations vnborne: it is a deluſion of Satan, to thinke otherwiſe, ſinne cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed: venter not on ſinne, vpon a preſumption of ſecrecie; birds of the ayre ſhall cary the voyce,<note place="margin">Eccle. 10.20.</note> and that which hath wings, ſhall tell the matter: many pennes are imployed this way, ſilently to obſerue and note humane paſſages, that ſecret workes of darkeneſſe, contriued in cloſeſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, may be publiſht hereafter on the houſe top;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21970:11"/> men blinded with the gliſtering out-ſides of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans Ieſuits <hi>pleaſure</hi> and <hi>profit,</hi> cannot ſee into priuate Studies, (the vnwilling priſons of rich Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords,) nor thinke of that which will diſgrace them in the ages to come.</p>
            <p>It is a rewarder of vertue, the proper end of Hiſtory, to reſerue worthy deeds, for imitation; a good worke, though it dye in doing, is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to it ſelfe, yet that ſome dull natures might be ſtirred vp the more, and all benefited by ſeeing gracious ſteps before them: this onely is exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a firme Dec ee from the ſtroake of death, to liue in Hiſtory, vertues preſeruatiue, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the deuouring graue, encouraging many to doe well, that they may heare well; to doe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in <hi>Ephratah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4 11. Math. 6.2.</note> that they may be famous in <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> Trumpets are for glozing votaries, who ſtudy rather to ſeeme, then to be good; let them hunt after applauſe, who know they deſerue not to haue it brought home vnto them: be ſilently conſtant in good courſes, commit your wayes vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſa. 37.5.</note> truſt in him, and he ſhall bring it to paſſe; retired vertue yet neuer loſt her praiſe.</p>
            <p>But to returne: the Hiſtory here meant, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially is Gods owne Booke, wherein we find the names of many vertuous daughters; as of <hi>Sarah, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.6. Iudges 5. 1. Sam. 1.25.3.</note> 
               <hi>Hannah, Abigail, Eſter, Iudith, Mary, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha, Lydia, &amp;c.</hi> That of our <hi>Sauiour</hi> is moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, enioyning the vſe of Hiſtory, to preſerue the memory of a good woman,<note place="margin">Math. 26.13.</note> 
               <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, whereſoeuer this Goſpell ſhall be preacht thorowout all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21970:11"/> the world, there alſo ſhall this that ſhe hath done, be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, for a memoriall of her:</hi> Hence it is that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Hiſtories in imitation of diuine, haue beene ſo carefull to preſent theſe iewels to poſterity, leſt any vertuous daughter ſhould be forgotten: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this I find, men generally too ſparing in praiſe of good women: ſeeing the Lord hath done it, men may proceed from a certainty of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to a neceſſity, his relatiue actions are for example, and ſo haue a binding power, ſaying to vs as our <hi>Sauiour</hi> did to the man in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Luke 10.37.</note> 
               <hi>Goe and doe likewiſe:</hi> it is a cuſtome as commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as ancient, at funerals, to mention thoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues moſt eminent in the parties deceaſed; whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer buries vertue in ſilence, or ſlubbers ouer worth in any by a careleſſe ſtile, commits a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold iniury; one againſt God the Donor, whoſe praiſe and glory is hindered; another againſt the perſons in whom it was, robd thereby of ſome part of their right; and a third againſt all ſurui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing followers, who ſhould be encouraged by ſuch iuſtice, to wreſtle with vice that ſo at laſt, they might goe home adorned with this Crowne of honour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let none enuy the dead; by negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to enroule good women amongſt this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of many.</p>
            <p>Secondly we haue here the manner how he commends her, not before he had giuen others their due praiſe: detraction from others, is no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ground, for the commendation of our owne; we may not ſteale from our neighbours, to enrich
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21970:12"/> our ſelues, or thoſe we loue, with goods or good name, nor diſpraiſe others, to augment our owne praiſe: it was an iniurious practice of the proud Phariſe,<note place="margin">Luke 18.14.</note> I am not as other men are, extortioners, vniuſt, adulterers, nor as this Publican: building his owne perfection vpon the weakeneſſe of his brother; concluding himſelfe (proudly) good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not ſo ſenſibly bad; ſound, becauſe not ſo apprehenſiuely ſicke as others: it is a cold kind of praiſe, that is drawne from the vices of any, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull demonſtration, taken from the worſer part: The relation of imperfections, is meat to feed malice onely, ſitter it is to bewaile them in ſecret, then to publſh them with delight for any end; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-talke in any places,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Quiſquis amat dictis abſcutum, rodere vitam.</p>
                  <p>Hanc men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam indignam nouerit eſſe ſibi. Aug.</p>
               </note> is too much faulty this way; it were good <hi>Catoes</hi> rule might be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; either good of men abſent, or nothing at all: ſo in matters of commendation keepe this method, obſerue and ſee amongſt the multitude if many be religious, vertuous, induſtrious, giue them firſt their due, then may you preferre your owne: good order obſerued in doing, beautiſies the action, and commends the workeman.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we haue here the matter of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: it is not ſaid, Many daughters haue beene beautifull;<note place="margin">Prou. 31.30.11, 4, 23.5.14.</note> fauour is deceitfull, and beauty is vanity: nor, Many daughters haue beene rich: houſe and riches are the inheritance of Fathers, which profit not in the day of wrath, but make themſelues wings, and fly away as an Egle: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it ſaid here, that many daughters haue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21970:12"/> beene, and are borne of high parentage,<note place="margin">Qui genus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat ſuum, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na laudat Sen.</note> it may be a benefit, no praiſe vnto women to come of great kinred; a good old ſtocke may nouriſh a fruitleſſe branch, a Noble family yeeld and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious progeny; the commendation runnes not of riches, beauty, or birth, (though theſe be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in their place and ranke,) but of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many daughters haue done vertuouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Teaching vs this leſſon, <hi>That</hi> vertue onely wins women true praiſe, and wiues deſerued commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: we find <hi>Sarah</hi> commended for obedience, <hi>Rebekah,</hi> for wiſedome, <hi>Rahel,</hi> for plyant loue, ſweetly-winning, and firmely-holding affability towards her husband; <hi>Abigail,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.3. Ruth. 3.11.</note> for a good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and <hi>Ruth,</hi> for vertue in generall: the Spirit of God moues the hard queſtion, not of a rich or beautifull, but, Who can find a vertuous woman? Men may eaſily find faire women wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, rich women proud, and ſurely, great wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men idle and impious, more then comly or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; more difficult to find a vertuous woman,<note place="margin">Iob 28.15, 16, 17, 19.</note> chaſte, humble, obedient, diſcreet, fearing God; whoſe ſweet compoſure of her ſelfe in all places and company, ſtirs vp in the beholders an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring affection; let him ſay, and thinke he is rich enough, her prize is farre aboue Rubies, no pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching pouerty could euer lodge with ſuch a Pearle: let him ſay, and thinke,<note place="margin">Prou. 18.22, 19, 14.</note> he hath found fauour with God, a prudent wife is from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21970:13"/> Lord, who muſt be prayed vnto before, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praiſed after: vertue is amiable, whereſoeuer found, but moſt of all in women; the weakeneſſe of their ſexe, addes a kind of ſtrength and luſter to their graces: vertue from beauty, euen in men is moſt attractiue, but in women, we find it hath a power ſtrangely coactiue, cauſing not onely the good, but the worſt of men to honour it: vertue hath had this priuiledge in all ages; beauty may pleaſe the eye for a time, as an obiect ouer-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull to vnregenerate nature, but by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of any of deaths meſſengers, it is put to ſlight, not daring to receiue a thought of death, much leſſe the ſight; riches may ſerue to gild o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer many imperfections in women, and make them ſeeme louely, which neuer were, while paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion guides reaſon, and the ſenſuall appetite vſurps authority to ſway the will, againſt the voyce of iudgement: the fleſh will be ſatiſfied with either of theſe, the mind fully contented with neither: both are momentary &amp; mutable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to make women honorable; that is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues prerogatiue Royall: honour is a vertue, and will be imployed about nothing but vertue; nor ſtick to any thing but what is immortall, free from change, as vertue is; were there ten thouſand ages, attended with as many diſeaſes, which ſhould come tumbling like <hi>Iobs</hi> meſſengers, one in the necke of another, yet vertue like ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable Caſtle, would ſtill flouriſh, out-facing the ſtormes of age, ſickneſſe, death, and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21970:13"/> graue: the more vertue ſuffers, the brighter it is,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ireſcit vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re virtus.</note> the longer it liues, the younger it growes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing by the communication, the oftner ſeene and vſed, the leſſe feared to be loſt; theeues can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſteale, nor time deface it: who can find a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous woman?</p>
            <p>Leſt any haſty to anſwere, ſhould be miſtaken, either in eſtimation of themſelues, affection to, or commendation of others, let vs enquire what it is to doe vertuouſly.</p>
            <p>It is no ordinary act of common ciuility, (as many in their conceits are miſtaken,) but an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall practice of ſomething more then morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: none can doe vertuouſly, without a habit of vertue; one action yeelds no denomination; and whoſoeuer hath the habit of any one in deed and in truth,<note place="margin">Augu. Epi. <hi>29.</hi> Hieron. Aqui. <hi>1.2.</hi> q. <hi>65.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> muſt of neceſſity haue the reſt in ſome degree; vertues, (excepting the intellectuall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which haue no ſuch dependance nor connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among themſelues,) are linkt as in a chaine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; if you be owners of one, the reſt will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>To this practice of vertue, there are three ſorts of vertues requiſite: all hauing, and keeping both their place and time, in a vertuous daughter, the eminency of ſome aboue others, breakes not the harmony: the firſt are intellectuall, and thoſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeculatiue, as knowledge to diſcerne, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to direct, and vnderſtanding to chuſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to both: or practicall, as prudence which is actiue in electing, and Art, which is operatiue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21970:14"/> in performing the election, according to the rules of vertue. The ſecond ſort are vertues mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſuch are Prouidence, or skill to giue good and wholeſome counſell, when occaſion is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to order all her affaires by the rule of right reaſon, to their proper ends, for the benefit of humane ſocieties: Iuſtice, by an vpright diuiſion, to giue to euery one their owne portion: Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, conſiſting in a diſcret limitation of paſſion and affection, about words, dyet, apparell, and pleaſure, that the fleſhy part ouer-ſway not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Fortitude and well-guided magnanimity, not againſt, but in defence of her husband, his perſon, goods, and good name, boldly to reſiſt all euill motions and temptations, with a conſtant oppoſition of carnall luſts, which fight againſt the ſoule.</p>
            <p>The third ſort, are vertues Theologicall, ſuch are thoſe precious graces of Faith to apprehend, Hope, to hold faſt, and Loue to glew her to the myſticall body of Chriſt; So that an vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſober, godly woman, is the vertuous daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter here meant; to be iudicious, induſtrious, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, in act &amp; exerciſe, is to doe vertuouſly; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daughters haue been ſo, many haue done ſo, and this is matter of commendation.</p>
            <p>Men may eſteeme thus of vertuous daughters in generall; it is not ſufficient in a husband, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſpeciall application: his owne, if ſhe ſtriue to doe her beſt, and be in any tolerable meaſure ſo qualified, muſt be preferd in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21970:14"/> as moſt vertuous and beſt for him; ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection we haue from the compariſon, which is my ſecond part, and comes in the next place to be diſcuſt; Though many daughters haue done vertuouſly, yet <hi>Thou excelleſt them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Commendation,</hi> it is ſomething beyond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon; to excell any, yeelds matter of praiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes; to excell and paſſe all, affords matter of admiration; which ſhewes the power of true af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to change in reſpect of it ſelfe, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things, and to produce effects aboue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: a hearty Louer can neuer be a ſound Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian; Grammarians acknowledge and make vſe of three degrees of compariſon; a true Louer admits no poſitiue, all his compariſons are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatiue; he thinkes none ſo vertuous, none ſo ſit for him, as his owne portion; and it is better, ſeeing the caſe thus ſtands, that all Grammarians ſhould be angry with vs, then one God offended by vs: whoſe will it is, as we ſee here, that one ſhould be preferred to all. <hi>Thou excelleſt all:</hi>
               <note place="margin">A good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muſt be ſingular in good.</note> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered not abſolutely, in regard of any one here meant, and pointed out in the Text, (though ſome might coniecturally appropriate it, to <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba,</hi> or to the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>) neither is it to be vnderſtood, as meant, or ſpoken of any, out of pride, vaine glory, flattery or a boaſting humour, (it is vnlawfull for men ſo to praiſe or preferre their owne,) but reſpectiuely, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers limitations and ſo applyable to any: as firſt, in regard of qualification, ſuch a one anſwering
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21970:15"/> the deſcription prefixt,<note place="margin">Videa ver. <hi>10.</hi> ad finem.</note> is preferd to all that doe not, and are not ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard of the husbands ſpeciall notice and knowledge, many haue done ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, but thou in my iudgement and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion excelleſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of his affection and liking, amongſt many, none appeare to him ſo vertuous.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in reſpect of his contentation with the endowments of his yokefellow, he is beſt pleaſed with her endeauours.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, in regard of his reſolution, vpon the former grounds, forſaking all, to cleaue vnto her, aboue all others; whoſoeuer meets with a vertuous Daughter, thus qualified, is bound in conſcience to thinke and ſay, <hi>To me thou excelleſt all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Aradicè <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Scandere. Aſicadere.</note>The word ſignifies to aſcend by climbing: as men in the field of warre doe aſpire after honour, ſo women in the calme ſchoole of vertue, doe ſtriue to goe higher, degree by degree, ſtep after ſtep; yeelding vs many leſſons worth our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that euery vertuous Daughter is humbly high-minded and holily-ambitious after the beſt things; climbing to aſcend, that they may excell in euery good worke: the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth elegantly expreſſe it of himſelfe, which I may here apply vnto them;<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.13.14.</note> they count not themſelues to haue apprehended, but this one thing they doe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting thoſe things which are behind, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21970:15"/> forth vnto thoſe things which are before; they preſſe towards the marke, for the price of the high calling of God, in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> it is the property of a diſpoſition baſely ſeruill, alwayes to looke downewards, and to thinke it ſelfe high enough, before there be any beginning to aſcend; whence it comes to paſſe, that many conclude they can doe nothing, becauſe they dare not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently thinke of the difficulty of doing; iudging ſinfull ſluggiſhneſſe, to be contented humility; when noble ſpirits aſpire daily after high and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult things inoſſenſiuely.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the way of vertue is the way to honour and preferment, in the loue of God,<note place="margin">Prou. 11.16.</note> and opinion of good men: in <hi>Rome</hi> there was no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Temple of honour, but by, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Temple of vertue: though it be narrow, yet it is an infaillible way: whoſoeuer climbes in by the windowes, as into the Church,<note place="margin">Iohn 10.1.</note> ſo vnto honour, is a theefe and a robber; by treading vpon the pins of an vnlawfull ladder, men and women may aſcend, not excell; either by the miſt of deſerued cenſure, they are couered, and ſo not regarded, or elſe through the ſuddaineſſe of a ſhamefull fall, they haue no leiſure to embrace their ſeeming happines; when vertue aduancing any, like the radiant Sunne expels all cloudes, and makes them ſhine in the fulneſſe of ſtrength; obſerue and ſee, whether ſuch as went in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther path, did euer finally proſper? When wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men riſe by falling, men by fawning and flattery,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21970:16"/> paying money, in ſtead of practiſing vertue, the higher they goe, the rarther will their infamy fly abroad; onely vertue leades to true honour.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that vertuous daughters hauing once begun, neuer leaue good and godly courſes, till they haue perfected their vertues by action: ſhe that lookes backe, is not ſit for the Kingdome of heauen; remember <hi>Lots</hi> wife: it is a miſerable thing to haue beene happy; when that may be verified of them which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes of his <hi>Galatians,</hi> Yee did run well: yee were vertuous, chaſte,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> ſober, religious: <hi>But, &amp;c.</hi> Goodneſſe is diſcerned and commended by continuance; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſolue to goe on, or begin not; climbing is painefull, yet men vſually deſiſt not; till they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the top, and end of their deſires; eſpecially if their aime be at ſuch fruits, flowres, &amp; ſhowes, as are in this eminent Garden of vertue; good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are no leſſe valiant, with vnwearied patience, to vndergoe the heat of the day, knowing they ſhall not be depriued of their hope; their labour cannot be vaine in the Lord:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. vlt. Reu. 2.10.</note> perſeuerance vnto death, brings a Crowne of life.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that ſuch vertuous women muſt not want encouragement by commendation: giue them the fruit of their hands, let their owne works praiſe them in the gates; <hi>Many daughters haue done vertuouſly, &amp;c.</hi> There was a feaſt ordained and kept in <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. vit, Rom.</note> called, <hi>Matronalia,</hi> in honour of thoſe women, which procured a peace betweene the <hi>Sabines</hi> and the <hi>Romanes;</hi> with diuers priuiledges
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21970:16"/> annexed vnto it, as to giue them place in all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike aſſemblies, to ſpeake no diſhoneſt words, nor doe any vnſeemely thing before them; it is a ſin to be ſilent in their praiſe, that deſerue it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided it be done iuſtly, ſeaſonably, &amp; diſcreetly: I would not wiſh men to dawbe ouer rotten poſts with deceitfull colours, to burden vicious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (their owne wiues,) with vndeſerued prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; nothing more fooliſh and ridiculous: I would not haue men make their wiues, though good and vertuous, the ordinary ſubiect of their talke, in all places and company; no cuſtome more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely, if not dangerous; but when conuenient occaſion is offered, to ſpeake the truth of them, for the glory of God, manifeſtation of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and excitation of others, by ſuch good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that vnderſtanding husbands, are beſt pleaſed with the vertuous actions of their owne partners: many haue done vertuouſly, but thou to me, in my eye and iudgement excelleſt all; A duty I confeſſe, eaſier to thinke, and ſpeake of, then to performe: an impure, adulterous heart, thinkes directly the contrary, that any mans wiſe his better th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is owne; Satan caſts ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rubs in the way, ſhewing men through a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull glaſſe, and ſaying, <hi>See,</hi> and obſerue in ſuch a one, handſomneſſe, beauty, wit, diligence, farre excelling thine; enioy her at leaſt in deſire; and preuailing paſſion, yeelding to this tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, blinds iudgement; ſo that many there are,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21970:17"/> who haue and doe deeme their owne choiſe worſt of all, nothing pleaſes, that paſſes from them, no, not when it is the ſame, which they approue and admire in others: therefore the vnderſtanding muſt be conuinc't, the heart ſeaſoned with grace, the eye emptied of adultery, and the mind freed from the reſtleſſe motion, and perturbation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing deſire of change, before any can ſay truly of his owne vertuous ſecond, <hi>Thou</hi> excelleſt all. Take <hi>Solomons</hi> counſell;<note place="margin">Pro. 5.15, 16, 17, 19.</note> drinke waters out of thine owne Ciſterne, and running waters out of thine owne Well, let thy Fountaine be bleſſed, and reioyce with the wiſe of thy youth; let her be as the louing Hind, and pleaſant Roe; let her breſt ſatisfie thee at all times, and be thou rauiſht alwayes with her loue; giue affection leaue here to extend her ſelfe ſomething beyond truth, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is no way to erre, or no danger in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this way.</p>
            <p>To wind vp both, the Commendation, and Compariſon on one bottome; I ſhall conclude all with the time, in certaine ſpecialties, by way of application.</p>
            <p>The whole may ſerue to informe vs, firſt, that men ſhould be experienſt, able to diſcerne good from euill, vertuous from vicious women, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they make choyſe of a wife, that men ſo ſoon as they are married, ſhould be able to commend good wines, is expreſt in the Text<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they ſhould be as able to condemne the euill and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, is neceſſarily implyed; none can commend
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21970:17"/> a good one, but he that knowes a bad; and can diſcerne thorow the vaile of hypocriſie &amp; maske of diſſimulation, leſt one be miſtaken for the other, vertue vnderualewed, and vice approued; ſuch euents are common, where experience is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: hence it is, many marry they know not what, and may amend their choice, they know not when: When <hi>Ceſar</hi> was to paſſe <hi>Rubicon</hi> againſt <hi>Pompey,</hi> he left the land with this reſolution, as I remember,
<q>That a man could be vndone but once;</q> As it is in the gouernment of a Common weale, or in the ordering of an Army, a Commander can erre but once, (which is a miſerable happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,) ouerthrow and ruine following ſo cloſe, he cannot haue leiſure to be twice faulty. So of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes it fals out in the choyce of a wife, men haue not leaue to change often, one bleſt or croſt, euer ſo, during life: it is a practice dangerous &amp; intolerable in a well-gouerned <hi>State,</hi> to force an vnion betweene young yeeres; where there is no actuall power to chuſe, nor iudgement to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne; common reaſon tels vs, we ſhould be long in doing that, which can but once be done, leſt after we vainely wiſh it were to doe againe: bead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, it is a long bargaine; raſh aduentures yeeld little gaine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are further informed, that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is the chiefeſt flowre in <hi>A good wiues garden:</hi> for this ſhe is commended, preferd for this; riches,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21970:18"/> beauty, parentage, fauour, and proportion grow in lower rankes, and ſerue to adorne the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; the heart is vertues place; which ſhowes it ſelfe to be aliue,<note place="margin">Math. 7.16.</note> by the preſent fruits of vertuous actions; none haue choſen well, who haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd any thing to this, in their choyce: looke firſt on beauty, and you buy a Picture; looke firſt on riches, and you make a purchaſe; looke firſt on parentage, &amp; you match with a multitude at one time; but looke firſt on vertue, and it is a marriage indeed, two made one by a myſticall vnion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting that betweene <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Church:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.26, 27, 28.</note> the Law may tye two together, that meet vpon ſiniſter ends, vertue onely vnites them; therefore this is moſt excellent and praiſe-worthy; all other flowres dye in Winter, this flouriſhes moſt in old age; others droupe vnder the ſtormy blaſts of hoary <hi>Autumne,</hi> while this enioyes a perpetuall Spring.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we are hence informed that wiues ſhould therefore ſtriue to excell one another in vertue chiefly:<note place="margin">Plut. vit Lyeur.</note> 
               <hi>Licurgus</hi> made the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> equall in liuings and riches: his reaſon was, that they might ſtriue to excell one another in vertue onely: I ſeeke not ſuch a Law, ſuppoſing equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of deſire this way, may well ſtand with ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of condition: the excellency of riches and pouerty conſiſting in this ability, through a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous diſpoſition, to make a right vſe of either: we ſee many contend for ſuperiority in place, who
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21970:18"/> ſhall ſtand, ſit, and goe before; we may obſerue women ſtriue with their neighbours, who ſhall excell in decking and trimming their bodies, adorning and ſetting forth their houſes, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new faſhions, and out-ſtripping one another in exceſſiue feaſting: euident ſignes of great light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to wreſtle about, or deeme themſelues the better, for any of theſe trifles: emulation onely in the race of vertue, is worth commendation; Couet earneſtly after the beſt things,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. vlt.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle, Who ſhall be moſt rich in grace; moſt zealous and forward in good duties; who ſhall excell moſt in the vertues of humility, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, chaſtity, modeſty, prouidence, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. ſuch couetouſneſſe is commendable, ſuch contention the iſſue of ſinleſſe-ambition: let all care giue place to this, all ſtrife be turned into this, how you may excell one another in vertue, ſo ſhall loue regaine her ancient ſoueraignety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt neighbous, in ſpight of enuy.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we may hence learne, that married perſons ſhould conſter the actions one of another in the beſt ſence; to ſay, and thinke, (if it be true in any tolerable manner,) their owne choyce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels all others: and that firſt, in token of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Gods diſpoſition, who ordaines meet matches, allotting to euery body his owne ribbe: ſecondly, to manifeſt their contentation with their portion, when they can ſay heartily, their lot is fallen out vnto them in a good ground:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21970:19"/> thirdly, for a teſtimony of the truth of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection each to other; it is one property of loue, to couer a multitude of infirmities, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to iudge that excellent, which is but weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good; wiues paſſing by their husbands faults, husbands pardoning their wiues failings, that ſo a good opinion may be ſtill kept warme in the lap of mutuall affection.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the husband muſt thus thinke of his wife, and ſeaſonably expreſſe it, for a comfort to her againſt all her paines and trouble in child-birth, and family affaires, as alſo to encourage her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though many daughters haue beene vertuous, yet none ſo ſit for me, thou excelleſt all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to that end it is required ſhe be, firſt, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, a profeſt ſeruant of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> going and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others with her in the way to heauen; for how can ſuch be ſaid to excell amongſt men, who are ſo farre from this ſpirituall exerciſe, of climbing <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, that they neuer yet lookt vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heauen, with any ſettled purpoſe to goe thither? vnder this I comprize piety, charity, &amp; ſobriety, in words, food rayment, pleaſure, &amp;c. ſecondly, that ſhe be oſſicious, a builder together with her husband; readie and willing, both in regard of earth and heauen, body and ſoule; vnder this, ſhe is enioyned to be louing, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, helpfull in all good things, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of her power; Let ſuch a husband ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21970:19"/> inricht, remember to be thankefull vnto God, who hath done more for him then parents, his purſe, or all the world could doe; good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants are a bleſſing, good children a greater, but a good wife beſt of all.</p>
            <p>Some may reply here, and demand, How can we ſay, as you teach, without ſinne, when we ſee and feele the contrary? I anſwere, firſt, it may be ſo, many daughters haue beene vicious,<note place="margin">Dub. pag. <hi>243.</hi> impoſt.</note> yours worſt of all; naturally women are waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, weake, vnwiſe, ſight, credulous, newes, louers, giuen to lies: Many haue beene and are irreligious, enemies to profeſſion in the powet thereof; Many are giuen to pride, idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wantonneſſe, drunkenneſſe; witneſſe thoſe conceited conditionall Lawes, attributed to <hi>Zaleucus</hi> the <hi>Locrian,</hi> reſtraining women, that none ſhould be attended with more then one maid in the ſtreet, except when ſhe was drunke; that none ſhould goe out of the City in the night, except ſhe went to commit adultery, and that none ſhould weare gold or embrodred appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, except when ſhe purpoſed to manifeſt her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a common ſtrumpet.</p>
            <p>Many are giuen to lying, ſwearing, curſing, brawling, and fighting, like deuils incarnate, (ſuch ribbes are <hi>Satans</hi> ſhaftes, taken from the ſides, to be ſhot againſt the heart of man to vexe him, and to be as rottenneſſe in his bones) and yours it may be for want of grace, are worſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21970:20"/> of all: of ſuch neuer thinke nor ſay, that they excell in vertue, it is no part of the Doctrine here taught, but the contrary; women muſt doe things praiſe-worthy, that will be praiſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, blame your owne choyce; beauty, or riches was the Starre that ledde you, how could you eſcape ſhippe-wracke? you ſought not for a vertuous mate, no maruell if you found her not: but ſhe was once better: take heede then; ſome vntoward behauiour in you, may occaſion thoſe vnruly paſſions in her: a wife is like a ſhippe, well ſteered, ſhe goes ſmooth, if otherwayes, ſhe be guided by an vn-skilfull hand, ſhe turnes and tumbles would make one ſicke to ſee her: how-euer, know it is a burden laid on you by the Lord, to chaſtiſe your former folly, trye your patience, or to exerciſe your skill.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſuppoſe many failings in your wiues, yet if there be a will to doe well, (a wiſe man may eaſily diſcerne betweene habituall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and intermiſſiue frailties,) deale with them as you would God ſhould deale with you,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Accept the will</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For the deed:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Suffering, is the way to victory; to yeeld vnto them in ſome things, is a meanes to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21970:20"/> make them more obedient in all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the wife muſt haue the ſame conceit of her husband, elſe the Ring goes not round. Though many ſonnes haue done vertuouſly, thou to me excelleſt them all: and to that end, hee muſt bee, firſt, iudicious, a man of vnderſtanding, able to manage the affaires of his generall, and particular calling;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7.</note> vnder this I containe wiſedome, knowledge, experience, ſobriety, Chriſtian care, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for his charge, &amp;c. want of diſcretion acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally begets contempt.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 5.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, he muſt be courteous in his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour towards her, (a churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be brought within the compaſſe of this round,) good words, and lookes, giue women great content, eſpecially from thoſe they loue: I would not haue men ſo ſoft and ſillie, as to be diſpleaſed with nothing, neither to be ſo hot, and haſty, as to bee angry with euery thing; there is a golden meane: and vnder this I place patience, bounty, familiarity, like that of <hi>Iſaak</hi> with <hi>Rebekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26.8.</note> encouragement in good and defence of her perſon, and name againſt all others: Let ſuch a wife ſo enricht, remember to pay the debt ſhee owes vnto God, of praiſe and thankes; is not ſuch a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band better vnto her then ten ſons?<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, I am ſo matcht as neuer woman was, many husbands haue beene vicious,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21970:21"/> mine worſt of all? I anſwere, Firſt, it may be ſo in your conceit onely, want of affection with deſire of change, may miſlead iudgement: Secondly, ſay it be ſo indeed, hee runnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, frequents Tauernes and Ale-houſes, miſ-pends his time and meanes in gaming, &amp;c. take-heede you bee no cauſe thereof; Many are ſo light-heeled, and nimble-tongued, their husbands haue no delight to ſtay within. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how-euer it be, prayers and teares will proue your beſt weapons, with a patient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of his reformation, knowing it to be the iuſt hand of God, for your youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wantonneſſe and neglect of his ſeruice: the beſt counſell I know to giue you, is,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pleaſe him, and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pray for him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, be you all aduiſed; if married, to examine your condition for a perfect vnion is attended with this opinion; if vnmarried, reſolue to match with none, except you bee thus perſwaded of them: reſiſt Satans ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, all carnall motions, whereby many vntoward marriages are made amongſt vs, that you may weare out this conceit each of other as your</p>
            <p rend="italic indent">Wedding-ring.</p>
            <p>The benefits following, which may moue
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21970:21"/> you to put it on, are many. Firſt, all harſh conceits are hereby preuented or remoued, what is done or ſpoken, ſhall be well taken; one weyghing ſtill the workes of the other, in the ballance of good-will, either finds none, or freely pardons the want of weight.</p>
            <p>Secondly, no ſtrife can be raiſed betweene you, which is not ſoone appeaſed; paſſion and ſuſpition may preuaile ſo farre, as to dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but ſhall neuer liue ſo long, as to put out the eye of affection: their iarres are attended with words, (loue offended cannot long be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,) words beget lookes, and lookes are followed with ſmiles, ſo the ſtorme is layd.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, good example is giuen, to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſeruants, neighbours, and to the Church of God: O, how pleaſant a thing is it, to ſee man and wife to ſpend their dayes in perfect amity? one bearing, the other forbearing, both ſtudying to giue content: ſo that other may ſee that happineſſe which they cannot attaine, and be driuen to admiration, though not to imitation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, hearty loue ſhall be maintained and encreaſed daily, ſo that you will neuer deſire to change, hearts nor hands, with any other; the longer you liue, the more louing you will be, ſuch vertue there is in this <hi>Wedding-ring:</hi> pray you may find it; endeauour to weare it, reſolue to liue and dye with it, that men may after fixe it as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21970:22"/> an Epitaph on your tombes, to be ſeene and read of all with iuſt applauſe.</p>
            <p>I end with prayer for you both: the Lord guide you with his Spirit, ſeaſon your hearts with his grace, and make you truly vertuous, that as <hi>Iſaak</hi> and <hi>Rebekah, Iacob</hi> and <hi>Rahel,</hi> you may build vp the houſe of your fathers, liue peaceably, and dye comfortably; that ſo this which hath beene ſpoken for you on the day of your meeting, may be verified of you, after the day of your parting.</p>
            <p>Many ſons and daughters haue done vertuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but you haue endeauoured to excell them all.</p>
            <p>To God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt, be giuen all honour and glory, now and for euer.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21970:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
